<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letter from Judah Kyriakos, bishop of Jerusalem, to
                    Papa bar Aggai</title>
                <title level="s">Digital Syriac Corpus</title>
                <author>Judah Kyriakos</author>
                <sponsor>University of Oxford</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Brigham Young University</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Initiative for Digital Humanities, Media, and Culture at Texas A&amp;M
                    University</sponsor>
                <funder/>
                <principal>Kristian S. Heal</principal>
                <principal>David G.K. Taylor</principal>
                <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dtaylor">David G.K. Taylor,
                    University of Oxford</editor>
                <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#abutts">Aaron Butts, The
                    Catholic University of America</editor>
                <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#kheal">Kristian S. Heal,
                    Brigham Young University</editor>
                <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz,
                    Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</editor>
                <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dmichelson">David A.
                    Michelson, Vanderbilt University</editor>
                <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                    Schwartz, Texas A&amp;M University</editor>
                <editor role="general editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#jwalters">James E.
                    Walters, Rochester College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#jwalters">James E.
                        Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#adirienzo">Annunziata Di
                        Rienzo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Syriac text transcribed by</resp>
                    <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#adirienzo">Annunziata Di
                        Rienzo</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>edited by</resp>
                    <name>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Annunziata</forename>
                            <surname>Di Rienzo</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>
                    <placeName>Jean and Alexander Heard Library System, Vanderbilt University,
                        Nashville, Tennessee, USA</placeName>
                </distributor>
                <authority>Digital Syriac Corpus</authority>
                <idno type="URI">https://syriaccorpus.org/686</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p/>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                        <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
                    </licence>
                    <ab>
                        <note>This electronic edition is designed for open access reuse. The Syriac
                            base text is in the public domain. The TEI XML edition is copyrighted by
                            James E. Walters and is released under a Creative Commons Attribution
                            4.0 International Public License (CC BY 4.0).</note>
                    </ab>
                    <ab>
                        <note>The HTML page is copyrighted by Vanderbilt University and released
                            under a under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public
                            License (CC-BY 4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).
                            Attribution for reuse should follow the suggested citation and also
                            credit the copyright holder of the TEI XML edition.</note>
                    </ab>

                </availability>
                <date calendar="Gregorian"
                    ><!-- Our date of publication of this XML document--></date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Digital Syriac Corpus is collaboration of University of Oxford, Brigham Young
                    University, Vanderbilt University, and the Center of Digital Humanities Research
                    (CoDHR) at Texas A&amp;M University. </p>

            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="syr">Unvocalized Syriac of any variety or period</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation>
                <origDate type="composition" from="0300" to="0400">4th century</origDate>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="ProofedDigitalEdition">
            <change when="2025-04-23" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#jwalters">Created:
                file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="BornDigitalDiplomaticEdition">
        <front>
            <div type="title">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Letter from Judah Kyriakos, bishop of Jerusalem, to Papa bar
                        Aggai</title>
                    <editor>
                        <name type="person">Annunziata Di Rienzo</name>
                    </editor>
                </bibl>
            </div>
            <div type="preface" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Preface</head>
                <div xml:lang="eng">
                    <p xml:lang="eng">This text is a born-digital edition of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Letter from Judah Kyriakos, bishop of Jerusalem, to <ref target="http://syriaca.org/person/669">Papa bar
                        Aggai</ref></hi>. The letter is part of a corpus of eight letters representing the
                        correspondence of Papa bar Aggai, early 4th-century bishop of Seleucia, with
                        some exponents of the western political and religious power. Beside the <hi
                            rend="italic">Letter from Judah Kyriakos bishop of Jerusalem to
                            Papa</hi>, the corpus includes: a letter from Eusebius of Rome to Papa,
                        a letter from the Empress Helena to Papa, a letter from Papa to the Empress
                        Helena, a letter from Jacob bishop of Nisibis to Papa, a letter from Ephrem
                        to Papa, a letter from Papa to the citizens of Nisibis, the letter sent by
                        the Western Fathers on the illegal removal of Papa. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="eng">
                    <p xml:lang="eng">This edition is based on the following manuscript witnesses: </p>
                    <div xml:lang="eng">
                        <l>Erbil 509 (olim Alqoš 169/ Baghdad 509), f. 71r/v (E) (the most ancient
                            and principal source, probably direct or indirect source for the later
                            extant witnesses);</l>
                        <l>Rome, Vatican Library, Borg. Sir. 82, f. 114v-115r (B);</l>
                        <l>Birmingham, Mingana Collection Syr. 47, f. 34v-35r (M<hi rend="subscript"
                                >1</hi><hi>);</hi></l>
                        <l>Birmingham, Mingana Collection Syr. 586, f. 103r/v (M<hi rend="subscript"
                                >3</hi><hi>);</hi></l>
                        <l>Trichur, Chaldean Syrian Church, APSTCH THRI 65, f. 48r/v (A) (the
                            manuscript has been digitized, and it can be viewed <ref
                                target="https://www.vhmml.org/readingRoom/view/511738"
                                ><hi>here</hi></ref>);</l>
                        <l>Baghdad, Chaldean Catholic Church. Patriarchate of Baghdad 377, f. 12r/v
                            (C) (the manuscript has been digitized, and it can be viewed <ref
                                target="https://www.vhmml.org/readingRoom/view/609956"
                                ><hi>here</hi></ref>).</l>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="eng">
                    <p xml:lang="eng">This text has never been published in any prior edition. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="eng">This edition should not be considered as definitive but as a
                        still in-progress material. </p>
                    <p rend="footnote text" xml:lang="eng">There is an old German translation of the
                        entire corpus (based on the Syriac text preserved in ms Borg. Sir. 82) in O.
                        Braun, "Der Briefwechsel des Katholikos Papa von Seleucia. Ein Beitrag zur
                        Geschichte der ostsyrischen Kirche im vierten Jahrhundert", <hi
                            rend="italic"> Zeitschrift für katholische Theologie </hi>18 (1894), pp.
                        163-182, 546-565.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="eng">An English translation is provided along with the Syriac
                        text.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="eng">This edition is an outcome of the Marie Skłodowska-Curie
                        Global Fellowship 2022 – Project "ForM - FORGED MEMORIES: the Church of Late
                        Antique Iran and the West", funded by the European Commission.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="text">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Text</hi></head>
                <p xml:lang="syr"> ܐ̄ܚܪܬܼܐ ܕܝܗܘܕܐ ܩܘܼܪܝܵܩܘܿܣ
                    ܐܲܦܸܝܣܩܘܦܐ ܕܐܘܿܪܸܫܠܸܡ ܠܘܵܬܹܗ ܕܦܵܦܵܐ.<pb n="E 71r; A 48r; B 114v; C
                        12r; M1 34v; M3 103r"/> </p>
                <p xml:lang="syr"> ܠܦܵܦܝܲܐ ܦܵܦܵܐ ܪܲܒܵܐ ܕܟܼܵܗ̈ܢܐ ܘܪܸܫܵܐ <pb n="B 115r; M1
                    35r"/>  ܕܐܸܘܲܢܓܲܠܣ̈ܛܐ: <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p>
                            <hi>M</hi><hi rend="subscript">1</hi> adds (ܟܹܐܡܲܬܼ ܕܐܲܪܒܿܥܐ
                            ܦܵܛܪܝܪ̈ܟܹܐ)</p></note> ܝܼܗܘܼܕܵܐ ܩܘܼܪܝܵܩܘܿܣ ܠܪܒܿܘܼܬܼ ܟܵܗܢܘܼܬܼܵܟ ܒܡܵܪܢ ܆ 
                    ܣܵܓܹܿܕ. ܐܸܫܲܥܝܵܐ ܢܒܼܝܼܵܐ ܩܲܕܡ ܐܼܡܲܪ ܥܠܲܝܟ. ܘܥܲܠ ܩܲܕܿܝܼ̈ܫܹܐ ܕܐܲܟܼܘܵܬܼܟ ܕܬܫܒܘܚܬܗ
                    ܕܡܵܪܝܐ ܡܼܢ ܣܵܘ̈ܦܹܝܗܿ ܕܐܲܪܥܵܐ ܒܗܿܘܢ ܡܸܬܼܟܲܪܙܵܐ. <pb n="C 12v"/> ܘܲܒܼܢܲܚ̈ܬܲܝ ܝܲܡܵܐ ܘܲܒܼܥܵܡܪ̈ܝ ܓܵܙܪ̈ܬܐ ܘܲܒܼܥܵܡܪ̈ܝ 
                    ܡܲܕܒܿܪܐ. ܘܡܼܢ ܪܸܫܵܐ ܕܛܘܼܪܹ̈ܐ ܢܸܩܥܘܲܢ ܡܼܢ ܚܘܼܠܵܢܝ̈ܗܘܢ. ܘܲܢܫܲܒܿܚܘܼܢ ܝܵܬܼܒܲܝ̈
                    ܫܩܝܼ̈ܦܹܐ܆ ܒܩܵܠܐ ܕܩܘܼ̈ܕܵܫܲܝܗܘܿܢ. ܒܣܸܡ <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                           > C ܒܣܸܡܘ</p></note> ܡܵܪܝ 
                        ܘܥܕܪܬܿ <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p>
                            <hi>M</hi><hi rend="subscript">1 </hi>C ܘܥܲܕܪܘ</p></note> ܠܲܡܕܝܼܢ̄ܬܢ 
                    ܩܲܕܿܝܫܼܬܐ ܇ ܚܲܫܹ̈ܐ ܣܒܼܝܼ̈ܣܹܐ ܘܐܘܼܠܨ̈ܢܹܐ ܥܲܡܘܼ̈ܛܹܐ ܕܲܒܼܗܘܿܢ ܐܸܬܼܢܲܨܲܚܼܬܿ܆
                    ܒܲܡܣܲܝܒܿܪܢܘܼܬܼܵܟ ܕܲܒܼܟܼܠܗܘܿܢ ܐܵܓܘܿܢܝ̈ܟ ܘܢܸܣܝܘܿܢܝ̈ܟ ܕܡܼܢ ܚܲܢ̈ܦܸܐ. ܘܥܵܩܬܵܐ
                    ܘܚܲܕܘܼܬܼܐ ܬܲܪ̈ܬܲܝܗܹܝܢ ܐܸܫܬܲܠܛ ܒܲܢ܆ ܥܵܩܬܼܐ̣ ܡܸܛܠ ܟܲܪܝܘܼܬܲܢ ܥܲܠ <pb n="M3 103v"/> ܪܲܒܿܘܼܬܼ 
                    ܟܲܗܢܘܼܬܼܵܟ. ܘܚܲܕܘܬܼܵܐܼ ܕܢܨܚܼܬܿ ܘܲܫܩܲܠܬܿ ܟܠܝܼܠܵܐ ܕܙܵܟܼܘܼܬܼܵܐ. ܘܪܲܡܪܸܡܼܬܿ ܠܥܹܕܬܵܐ
                    ܒܡܘܼܟܵܟܼܵܟ ܕܥܲܠ ܐܲܦܹܝ̈ܗܿ. ܘܗܸܢܹܝ̈ܢ ܗܵܠܹܝܢ ܡܼܢ ܣܲܓܝܼ̈ܐܐ ܐܸܬܿܛܒܒܿ ܒܡܲܫܡܲܥܬܼܵܐ
                    ܕܗܹܠܹܢܹܐ <pb n="A 48v"/> ܡܲܠܟܿܬܼܵܐ. 
                    ܘܐܝܟ ܕܨܵܒܲܝܵܐ ܕܲܒܼܟܼܠܗܘܿܢ ܐܬܪ̈ܘܬܼܵܐ ܕܬܹܒܼܢܹܐ ܘܲܬܼܪܡܪܸܡ ܥܹܕܿܬܹܗ ܕܡܫܝܼܚܵܐ ܒܟܼܠ
                    ܨܹܒܼܬ̈ܝܼܢ ܆ <pb n="E 71v"/>
                    ܝܲܬܿܝܼܪܐܝܼܬܼ ܆ ܒܲܡܕܝܼ̈ܢܵܬܼܐ ܪܵܘܪ̈ܒܼܵܬܼܐ ܆ ܨܵܒܲܝܵܐ ܕܒܲܡܕܝܼܢ̄ܬܵܐ ܕܝܼܠܟܼܘܿܢ ܣܵܠܸܝܼܩ 
                    ܬܹܒܼܢܹܐ ܥܸܕܿܬܵܐ ܠܡܵܪܝܵܐ ܡܫܝܼܚܵܐ. ܘܒܼܵܥܝܵܐ ܡܲܦܣܵܢܘܼܬܼܵܐ ܡܼܢ ܐܲܒܼܵܗܘܼܬܼܟܼܘܿܢ. ܘܥܲܡ
                    ܡܲܦܣܵܢܘܼܬܼܐ ܡܸܠܟܵܐ. ܘܐܲܝܟ ܕܡܸܢܵܗܿ ܐܬܼܦܩܿܕܬܼ ܠܪܒܿܘܼܬܼ ܟܵܗܢܘܼܬܼܟܼܘܿܢ ܟܹܬܼܒܹܿܬܼ.
                    ܐܲܢ̄ܬܿ ܕܹܝܢ ܡܵܪܝ. ܐܲܝܟ ܪܚܡܲܬܸ ܐܲܠܵܗܵܐ ܕܒܼܵܟ܆ ܣܥܼܘܿܪ. ܘܐܵܘܕܲܥܹܝܗܿ ܐܲܝܕܵܐ ܕܥܵܕܪܐ
                    ܠܗܿ. ܟܲܕ ܡܸܬܼܚܲܪܪܐ ܡܼܢ ܟܸܫܠܵܐ. ܨܲܠܵܐ ܥܠܲܝܢ܆ ܘܥܲܠ ܡܲܠܟܵܐ ܙܲܟܵܝܐ ܒܪܵܗܿ
                    ܩܘܼܣܛܲܢܛܝܼܢܘܿܣ: ܘܥܲܠ ܟܠܗܘܿܢ ܦܵܠܚܹ̈ܐ ܕܡܲܠܟܿܘܼܬܹܗ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Translation</hi></head>
                <div type="rubric">
                    <p xml:lang="en">Another [letter] from Judah Kyriakos, bishop of Jerusalem, to
                        Papa. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="body">
                    <p xml:lang="en">To Father Papa, high priest and first of the evangelists (sic)
                        , Judah Kyriakos pays respect to your high priesthood in our Lord. The
                        prophet Isaiah has predicted about you and about the saints like you: The
                        glory of the Lord is proclaimed through them from the ends of the world, and
                        by the sailors (lit. those who go down to the sea) and the ones who inhabit
                        the islands and those who live in the desert; and from the top of the
                        mountains may they cry out from their caverns, and may those who sit on
                        steep rocks glorify in the voice of their holiness (cf. Isaiah 42, 10-11).
                        Rejoice, my lord. You helped our holy city. [There was] frequent suffering
                        and dark oppression in which you triumphed by your endurance in all your
                        struggles and trials from the pagans. Both distress and joy occupied us: the
                        distress caused by our sadness on your high priesthood’s behalf, and joy,
                        since you triumphed and received the crown of victory, and you exalted your
                        church through your lowliness on its behalf. And these are those things
                        among many that were reported in Empress Helen’s hearing. Accordingly, she
                        desires to build up in all places and exalt the church of Christ with every
                        adornment, especially in the great cities. She desires that in your city of
                        Seleucia, a church be built to the Lord Christ. And she seeks permission
                        from your Fatherhood, and with the permission, counsel. And since I was
                        commanded by her, I wrote to your high priesthood. You, then, my lord, as a
                        friend of the God who [is] with you, provide and show her [your] helpful
                        hand, while not taking offense. Pray for us and for the victorious emperor,
                        her son Constantine, and for all the servants of his kingdom. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
